hello everyone it is
meeting
of the active inference textbook group
cohort one
it is the final meeting of this
section
it's july 28 2022
and we are going to be uh especially
thinking about
feedback and structuring on this
textbook group
on how the first
half of the first cohort
went
and also
the ways that over
quite literally the coming minutes and
hours and days we will be able to
implement structures
to improve
our experience for those of us who are
continuing on to part two
covert one
as well as those who are joining for a
new cohort
in the onboarding page there are two
columns
with check boxes
and
clicking these check boxes
will sign you up to continue on in
chapter six or ten for cohort one
as well as
or alternatively
to join in chapters one through five
with cohort two so select one or both of
these boxes if you'd like
to be continuing
on
um
that's the onboarding note
and again other than that which i hope
those who are here or watching live
update according to how they want
um
other than that
we're going to be talking about future
textbook groups and other things like
that
and then also just on the informational
briefly on the future textbook group
page
here's the link to share with people to
join future textbook cohorts so to join
in
and then also please fill out this
feedback form it's really important that
even if people think they have limited
or
non-valuable feedback that
they provide it because
whether it's on this page directly where
everyone can edit and so every thought
that somebody has like even if right now
they can just edit this page
or
in this more anonymous and asynchronous
mode or through direct communication
but we're experiencing it
and so we have the best insight at this
point
into how to improve it and the
affordances that we're seeing today
or the the
state updates or however you want to use
ontology terms to describe it but what
we're seeing today
we can do
so we should have a fun discussion today
on some of those topics
and then also look towards project ideas
many of which are related to the
educational process
and
others which are
building on education into research
and application and so there will be
spaces for those as well
let's begin though on this future
textbook groups page
and
anywhere where people want to jump in
writing or speaking
how are we going to
summarize and distill
the experience of the last few months in
this textbook group
and bring it towards improvements in our
coming
cohorts
yeah i think having worked examples um
as i've talked about and um discussed
with brock like
in jupiter notebooks or like even um
like simple like did you understand the
material like question and answer like
quizzes at the end of each chapter or
um something like that i think which
just would be useful like to
gauge your own understanding like if
there is like a definition or
something that we can directly refer
back to in the text that'd be useful
okay worked examples
yes um
[Music]
great and
the questions could also include
little tests of knowledge not every
question needs to be
throwing a baseball into the deep
unknown
it can be
literally clarifying
for someone who believes that an answer
is in the
known unknown space
i i believe there's an answer for this i
just want to clarify for my
understanding
but also once you've clarified that and
especially if you did just clarify it
then write that example
because many of these are opportunities
for worked uh examples
and working examples work in certain
situations
for formalisms for example
it might also work for formalisms that
aren't mathematical
like
here's the system this way or this
phenomena how do these ontology terms
map
or if this is the blank then what is the
other thing
okay
so we have
okay anyone else just go for it or let's
just continue to edit and organize and
add notes and just have more because
many
people are having any
thoughts on directions to go
and just like what is the space of some
improvements that we can explore
and then how will we
be implementing some of these changes
and then in cohort two and someone's
like it could be this way and they've
thought of something that's new and not
on this list we added if it's on this
list we say awesome
we agree join us and do it
anyone else with raised hands or we can
look more at a few other sections before
going to the projects
like why she different regimes of uh
attention
i think one way that we can structure
that is
by clarifying what practices
were
explicating and where those practices
can take place
so then because
the reality is and
people who are here or listening and
replay can give their input
many people
may not
have known what exactly to do
to engage with the material
there's a textbook
there's some regular meetings there's an
information resource
and it's like an infinite game
to
structure
beneficial engagement
and where the rubber hits the road is
like being clear about what practices
people can engage in
so if we have math
like not
everything has to be
fractaled out into sub-sub-sub-groups
just including many of the practices
like if you want to do art about active
inference
here's a practice and then if people are
engaging in that practice it does like
create kind of like a group or a guild
engaging
in that performance
so
however people think like what are
useful
minutes and seconds
that actually help learning active
inference
and we'll be able to have a perspective
on that question in
years from now that's very different
based upon better understandings of
competencies and the fundamentals and
the approachment to the area
however i think the practices table and
providing feedback and then
[Music]
sharing and communicating how we're
using practices
to increase understanding
could be very important
for those who are learning and learning
how to learn
jessica and then anyone else
uh yes um i think to build up on sort of
like blue suggestion i'm thinking that
on
like in someone like all the courses
that i've taken um you have like all the
participants giving
sort of like feedback uh as part of the
learning process you give feedback on
like the other participants work
and so it could be that it's like
there's an exercise and everybody has to
like fill it up and etc
and then um the other participants or
like it could be like two or three and
so not everybody has to do everything um
so it's like yeah two three people you
read like it's like jessica's like uh
answer and give a feedback and you know
so on
um because in that way by um having to
critique or like analyze other people's
work it helps you think through
on the material itself
and
and yeah
so that's like another way um of also
like learning again
there's also amazing like yeah you can
make you could be probably like making a
mistake also not applying it correctly
but it's like a tool to help you think
through the material by
analyzing somebody else's work and while
also you know initially also having to
do on yourself and then hearing also the
feedback that other people are going to
be giving you
so i was kind of like an idea that came
to mind like
making reference from like other
experiences
thank you jessica
yes um
i
think that's a great area to
keep in mind
and to balance
as our
cohorts
build and so on
like who's on the supply and who's on
the demand side of that
so to speak like who is actually
offering the feedback
and then who's the people who are
wanting feedback
like some of these projects are
things where the person
was able to be
[Music]
brought in to another project
like
the
like noah's and mike's work
bringing them into synchronous and
asynchronous resources that are already
happening
provided them with at least a first step
for continuing on their journey
others
are um
they're in different areas and so how to
keep it open when people have ideas
ranging from
educational improvements
to robotic
deployments
what kind of feedback they need and then
how to balance like the excitement
around applying active inference
with
what it means to learn
like there are biochemistry classes it's
not all just biochemistry lab
but who's to say that's even
the best way or anything like that it's
just we want to make sure that
we keep it all in mind jessica
um yeah and i think this um
suggests an idea it's not connected to
on someone's project or in a 16 project
it's more like
an exercise so there's like you know
short exercise that it's going to be
testing you know variational influence
or something like that and
and then um
yeah like every participant in the class
go yeah actually does the exercise
and then it's assigned to
other people in
the cohort and to
analyze that person's submission and so
it's like yeah three people in the
course like analyze like jessica's you
know submission and give feedback and
like yeah it's gonna be like for
everybody everyone and we'll be getting
um three um
three feedback on like how they apply
the terms or like
you know there are other ways that they
could be done etcetera and
i mean if some of the things are like
math related like
i will have to see and
because then the answer is gonna be more
clear it's not gonna be as subjective
um
but it's more like you know there's a
short exercise
everybody does the exercise and then
some people then get to review that
um you know that answer of the person
and give feedback on that so it's like
separate from an actual project
okay makes sense it's kind of like a
combination of having a good example
questions
with an organizational structure and
then like you said balancing like where
there might be
a clearer
uh
measuring stick
like was this
the right equation
or the right calculation or not
versus um
how did
this usage of affordances in a new
context
make sense to you
and um
yeah also it's not just about getting
feedback on the person's idea it's like
the practice of providing
constructive ideally written
comments
is super important like the secret side
of the questions is
the discourse
um
[Music]
where the kinds of things that questions
and ideas that
send people on thought excursions and
research rabbit holes
we can
collaborate on that response together
and it doesn't have to be the end-all
be-all
but sometimes by putting like a seed
into the workspace by putting like a
prompt or a question
ten people could write for five minutes
and then there would be 50 minutes of
writing on that topic from different
perspectives
whereas if there's 10 people also there
could be five minutes of discussion
which might add more seeds onto the
table and it might
continue to invoke
whimsy
or it might continue to instruct if
there was a broad uncertainty that that
five minutes of discourse resolved
i think like
for the questions and it's like somebody
has like a question that they're trying
to understand and everybody's giving
it's the crowd source um answer and
helping you know
sense make on the meaning
of on how things are
with the other exercise i think similar
to i think what blue wants to do like
with the short um
like exercises to test whether people
know the concept or not
it's just like adding like by having
people critique other people's work and
having to like critically think through
the answer
is another level of learning
because you it's not just like oh i
think this is the answer to this it's
like no i actually have to understand
and
one day concept that i'm using to
evaluate
an answer
and then also evaluate the person's
answer
and
kind of compare and contrast
and that like having to make
that exercise of critical thinking
i think helps people um
learn like in a more in-depth way
because you have to think through your
own
thinking process and like what things
mean what somebody else was saying etc
and
and yeah and i i've seen it apply to
like writing i mean i guess it's maybe
like easy after like writing courses and
things like that um
but yeah it's like another way of um
yeah like processing through the
information
and and then also um
it also maybe like reduces the burden on
maybe like a person having to like go
through everybody's answer and making
sure like yeah like i am the teacher
correcting everybody's answers like it's
yeah you're sharing the responsibility
around everybody in the group
of
you know like kind of answering you know
like you know evaluating people's like
responses to an exercise
thank you brock and then anyone else
with the race hand
uh just to agree with jessica and the
last part would i was going to add that
but um
yeah that just
systematically created creating a
systematic affordance for people to
review or
provide some
validation that it's
correct or on the right path or
whatever um
will reduce the burden there and
uh
teaching
is probably the best way
to learn
um
it's
uh
learning how to learn is
it's like difficult to do without um
teaching
like learning
self-learning is about teaching yourself
to get better at teaching you get better
at teaching yourself
thanks um
which
continue
just the
circle back that does kind of require
some metastructure to like
create examples or source them or
whatever
and then provide them
[Music]
um
so i'm not
sure
outside of the
project that i put on there and
maybe it's kind of related to jakobs as
well but
outside of those two things i'm not sure
we have a clear
affordance to do that yet so
for coming up with examples of
yeah like examples to work or whatever
yeah like sort either sourcing them and
then putting them in a structure that
says oh this is for
section the chapter one or whatever 1.1
or whatever
this is uh so not questions that are
related to specific parts of the
textbook with people to work through but
what kind of table or structure
it could be i guess virtually the same
but instead of a question a question
somebody is asking it's an example
for other people to answer maybe with an
answer
that they can see like if they want to
reveal it or whatever but
these does that make sense
yes
um that's that's what it could be
an example to work through in this
course it doesn't mean this exact tape
but just make sure that we have written
it down
and everyone can be
contributing to like write it down and
what the structure is because it's not
like this is a
um impossible affordance
we can spin up the table right now and
template it and just start to design it
and over the coming weeks we have time
to digest all these different inputs
to to make it so you know in a few weeks
it will fly by but we might be able to
be implementing these things
i wanted to ask what practices did
people
feel like they engaged in
fruitfully
whether it's on here or not just when
you feel like you were participating in
the active textbook group what did you
feel like you were doing and how did it
help
equation translation that was like the
most helpful thing that i did
um and i don't think it's there in the
well i guess it's kind of there
it was like to copy the equations down
but like putting them into natural
language was probably like
the thing that i did that was maybe most
useful for
myself and others
yep
it was a great practice
and
um
[Music]
it
leads to and scaffolds so many other why
is it this way what does this mean what
are the examples it's not like the
prerequisite per se
it's possible to ask questions without
having the natural language description
but whether it's a basic or a multi-line
equation
it helps
bring consilience to that discussion
because there's a non-zero probability
that then
a term is going to be used loosely or
it's going to be used one way then it's
going to be conversationally used
slightly differently
or people will
not
agree on which ontology terms
are invoked or not
which can then have every equation start
to spiral off into every possible
ontology term
and they very well might actually
connect
that way
but being able to see
what is variational free energy
and if there's some term that is being
connected to variational free energy
that's not being described in the
equation
that's fine
like least squared error
isn't in
the linear regression y equals mx plus b
so there can be formal and informal
concepts that are super important for
understanding
that aren't
with a symbol
but this was a great
way to be clear what the symbols
actually are
what other practices did people feel
like they
benefited from
what would they recommend for a daily
schedule for somebody who wanted to
learn a lot
i think
plus one
there on uh
blues
um like
writing the equations which is like
maybe a super
simple but open-ended almost kind of
version of
jessica's suggestion um
but also in general uh
just adding stuff to the
coda
um
asking questions
like
if you read and you don't ask a question
did you
really grapple with it at all i don't
know um
how do we improve
thinking by writing in the actual number
of typed words
that people add in
as a proxy
during a discussion is one thing but
even just afterwards or on their own
time frame
how can we
have
10 people who do read a chapter just
scaling numbers
each of them
could think of several questions
ranging from simple
i wasn't sure about
to simple again like more like an
example one like what are the three
kinds of this
and it's totally known and the answer is
fully listed
to researchy questions but
how could we have many more inputs
in terms of
the questions that people
are asking
do people feel like they
wrote questions in their own
notes
but didn't bring it into shared
workspace or do people feel like for
themselves or or others that they
observed that the questions weren't
actually
phrased
um jessica then anyone else
yes i mean i was gonna share more about
the
student practices and but i guess like
first of all answer like the last
question you
i mentioned
there were things that i didn't put in
the general um
textbook thing which were more about
parsing information and which was like
helping me
connect the dots and and
synthesize an information
which ali actually helped me a lot also
um
with some of that and but those things
were sort of like
personal for me to like try to make
sense of the material
and in terms of the student practices
i
like
initially i was thinking to do like
every day
and you know like an hour
each for like the reading and maybe like
an hour for the math and to kind of get
foundational things um
but then i found it was like better for
me to
maybe dedicate like a longer period of
time on one day or two days for the
reading so i'm supposed to like a little
bit of the reading more like chunk more
and you know two three hours in one day
and then maybe like follow up another
day with like a longer period of reading
as well instead of daily reading a
little bit
and
and i think that's more because i guess
for memory i mean they do say to do like
repetition for memory but i think like
for me it was like well really longer
and you know have like
the material fresh in your mind as like
really as opposed to going every day and
and then like for the math because i
guess there's less of
them
you know keeping the material price in
your mind like yeah like daily i was
trying to do that so then it fell off a
little bit on on that part
but yeah like kind of at least one every
day like but four days a week at least
like an hour so like trying to focus on
the math
but yeah that's kind of how
my practice
you know
yeah
develop over time through the course
so the textbook
is for
as the
like the research people who want to
apply in their research if we remember
like from the introduction
provide readers with the ability to
understand and use active inference in
their own research
we'll have a better sense after part two
with a more
applied
side
[Music]
who might the next cohort of the
textbook group
be in and communicate to
yes
over many iterations and you know can go
many ways but when people are thinking
like in the next few weeks
who
blue ro okay
can we review which questions and
understand
because i i don't quite
understand how
like so if we go to the um like if you
want to check out the questions check
out like chapter two like and a lot of
the questions were so if you scroll down
um keep scrolling keep scrolling like um
i'm trying to think about
which ones that were skipped let's see
and also there's no skipping there's
what we can address in the one hour or
two hours
right but i mean like we can raise our
attention to all the important questions
yeah it was just like um and then i
realized like most of my questions were
like of a largely technical nature
so let me scroll through the coda um
and see if i can find them but it was
like
in
chapter two it was
like let's see
um like the general thing to me is how
how can we
um among other things
prevent question
self-censorship and filtering
well
that question isn't just like this one
like genius meets genius perfectly
framed specific answer that will be
understood in one sentence but that
question is like a broader space of
prompts that don't necessarily
have any prior on whether it has to do
with an application or it could be a a
technical question
well so it would use reference yeah good
it was early it was like in chapter two
and chapter three and there were like a
lot of questions um i'm trying to like
look at the specific i'll have to look
at my own code instead of watching you
beautiful people but um
it was
and like it it just happened early like
in those meetings um and and it's not
that there wasn't time like that we
didn't address the questions in order it
was like let's skip this because it's
technical let's skip this because it's
technical so i just stopped putting my
questions in because i feel like they're
technical
like what does this little squiggly
symbol mean and and that's why like for
me the translation of equations into um
natural language was the most useful
thing because i feel like all of my my
questions are technical like related to
the math
so i stopped entering them into the coda
because they were just
skipped over
okay thanks well
you appreciate it
um
again i
personally
hope that we can have structures that
uncouple
the perceived importance of real-time
speech from the contributions that
people make
so that we can be really clear about
like which questions we're going to be
addressing in conversation
but
and and use conversation for what it can
bring
many things
and then
have
200 questions in chapter two
with many upvoters or with whatever
mechanism that brings different
questions to the four
so there isn't even like the
plausibility of being skipped it's just
a question of like what will we raise up
and focus on individually and as a group
from the many many questions of
different kinds
that
support
a beginner
with fundamentals
and a pre-beginner with background and
somebody who's asking research
questions as well
so i think one simple thing
is uh
if if you go back to the questions um
table like
you have a um interest column here
um
[Music]
interesting yes even better
um
maybe there is a
what we will address in the netcoming
live stream or a session kind of table
that is taken from the questions table
but the questions table has no such
like
projection of what is interesting or not
in some especially in some
one-dimensional kind of like
yes or no
thing um
it's just a separation of
random
things prompts questions
and then
there is some process to get it to
what will what will be addressed in the
live stream
that
um
[Music]
again there's ways to like try to do
things like randomization or trying to
like ensure that you know
we don't continuously ask
focus from one person
or things like that
the popularity doesn't kind of win the
day
um
there's more complex ways to do this
that are
kind of
almost like decision making processes
like um
ephemeral group processes and things
like that but um
yeah i think just separating them
it would be helpful there at least
um another thing might be like zoom you
could do breakout rooms
maybe that's not the format
but um
again just
uh that's kind of an ephemeral group
process thing like
perhaps everyone doesn't want to focus
on the same questions
should there be temporary
temporary split averaging of attention
and that for some short period of time
and then
recombine
don't know what that means for a live
stream or recording precisely but yeah
that's
possible solution
yeah thanks
gather is awesome for these things but
it does require clarity around how it's
going to be done
like mass one-on-one breakouts mass
smaller great breakouts and rearranging
people using their spatial location to
express
different things and
assemble into different ephemeral teams
okay let's look at some
project
ideas okay
so if for those who are here or not i
hope i'm not misrepresenting anything
um mike
brought up some token economies that's
something that we've been actively
going towards in active block prints
um
so i'll just add just a note column
in active lock for ins
as well as as mentioned earlier um
working with
noaa
on some more some related topics
okay
audiobook recording of a textbook
just as we go through these projects
um i've recorded
the first
chapter and the preface type materials
do people think that an audio recording
has
utility
and if so is anyone interested to pursue
this avenue with blue and i
because it's very defined
and it involves
primarily the equations having natural
descriptions and then just reading
and it can go many other directions too
but this is like um
kind of a clear accessibility affordance
for different participants that might be
interesting as well as just get out
there on like youtube and other channels
as having that
artifact blue
i do think it's useful obviously if i've
elected to
i didn't realize i signed up to be the
participant lead but i'm so happy to do
it
co-lead colleague um but but i do think
it's useful as someone who drives like a
considerable amount of time like every
day
um
if it's not like i'm not a very good
auditory learner but it does help to
like reinforce the concepts um and i i
just wanted to mention
um
even if like you're not comfortable
perhaps like doing the math or
reading the textbook um
daniel thinks he can read it until it's
perfect um i would prefer to
do some video or audio editing
um so that's also an option is to do
audio editing like where he's
like you know you occasionally like
stutter daniel does it very infrequently
but but there's the occasional
tripping over a word or like um saying a
word twice like when you lose your place
or something like that so video or audio
editing um i do it with windows video
editor but like audio editing is also
another possible affordance there and it
would involve like you know reading
along with textbook to make sure that
it's accurate that no sentences are
skipped and then to just splice out any
like mishaps or just ask him to
re-record
the you know markup blanket for
precision just so you can place it over
the trip trip up if needed
yeah thanks definitely we would do a
multi-part
i i just did one pass on the first
chapter no equations etc draft but okay
anyways just so people who are
um
interested here or re-watching can know
about this okay
resources for conducting research or
developing active inference agents ways
to facilitate the starting of that work
for participants just a seed idea
um
a lot of this is going to be explored in
part two
because it's a recipe
for designing the models and we'll have
a lot of infrastructure around that as
well
so i hope whoever wrote this
continues in that interest
and
builds that starting point for
conducting research or developing agents
based around what they learn and see in
part two
okay
um
also
typing just directly in the code is a
little better than commas because
sometimes it's hard to understand what
the comments are
like referring to
like okay complete mathematical overview
of active inference
derivations of key results maps of
equations
yes
all awesome thank you jacob for
suggesting this
um
i think the closest related works
are in the actin
phontology and in knowledge engineering
and other areas too
um
and i hope that we're on this
path
however jock up or anyone else wants to
connect on that
okay
actin foundations
um so here we added this page
if um
brock or anyone else wants to add any
comments
or
describe how some of these comments can
be integrated with
textbook group
um
short answer is i'm not entirely
sure the precise way to integrate it
with the textbook group
but um
they're
just um
perhaps this is related to questions
making questions
um
removing the stigma or whatever like
it's just helpful i think to have some
affordance or regime of attention or
whatever
thing that says
hey
if you don't understand this thing about
active inference
that's a foundational thing like
okay i get entropy but
and i get energy like the basic concepts
of them but like when you're subtracting
them what the hell are we talking about
you know
um and then maybe there's you know some
follow-on questions
about
mathematically what entropy is
mathematically what is energy or you
know what does shannon introduce
specifically what is the difference
these sorts of things um
a it's that
an affordance for that but b it's also
just acknowledging like um
there's a wealth of knowledge already
here
it's not
a complete mystery what those back
background foundational things are
it's or what learners might want to get
out of
um
some relatively short course to like
get up to speed
and feel real confident reading
the textbook
and so there's a kind of top-down
uh
affordance there too i think
that needs to be made for um
people that can say hey there's a
bunch of equations over or examples over
here that are these are the most helpful
ones i've found for
understanding
what bayesian inference really is um how
that really works um
so
i guess it would be those two things but
if you look into the project um
notes there on that project idea um
thing it's
there's a little more
uh
detail of um
[Music]
yeah just a couple bullet points there
of just
it's it's really hard for people i think
to get into a new thing if there's not a
model
if you do chemistry without bore's model
like good luck
if you have to jump especially to
something like
electron probability clouds or something
it's just like why would you do that
when you have a perfectly good periodic
table
and simple discrete you know and
it's enough even to do basic physics
right
like newtonian stuff right and so
um
you need a model like i think a lot of
people
history
is helpful there very minimal amount but
just a this is where this came from this
is why it's relevant um
it's really hard for people i think
to blindly calculate without that sort
of
simple context
so
just
kind of made a very rudimentary
still kind of scaffolding it um
coda
but all it's already linked in that
project row but i'll put it in that
sub page there too um
super
work in progress
but um
yeah i mean the idea is just there's
these questions are going to be asked
over and over and over again there will
be people coming from a more
mathematical more physics a more
neuroscience a more from different
backgrounds
and so why
pretend like that's not happening or
reinvent the wheel every time somebody
asks a question like just having a
central resource where people can get a
lot of value but also maybe
ask a question that's a little more
they might not want to ask and seem like
it's too simple or it's too whatever um
in
the live stream
so
okay thank you
any other comments or thoughts on this
otherwise we'll just continue on for the
final minutes
okay
textbook enrichment
yes i hope everyone continues to
annotate figure out also things on their
own and explore
and like
we're building something really powerful
with annotation
so i hope that people can um continue to
be enriching
with the structures that we're building
but yes
so much of what this group has been
about has been about textbook enrichment
and improvement
robot modeling unless anyone has other
comments i think learning from jf
and
staying in part two will help
and um yeah jessica and then anyone else
sorry i think i didn't raise my mind
yes well
any general comments that people want to
provide on the textbook group
i think the live streams are super
important
for the lab and the whole space
for a maybe obvious reason
the textbook group is equally
important
and these are like the two most
important things that
can add value to this space and the lab
participants so
that's it
indeed
glad that those who have made it
this far
see that
and
over the right time scales
in the right way
we see more and more
vistas to increase the accessibility and
rigor of active inference
so i hope we can hold that frame
and focus our attention
[Music]
to
provide these functionalities
because if it's stateable it's doable
in a way
and
if no one from the first cohort wants to
be an active facilitator or steward
for
textbook group 2
some of these changes will be integrated
the more people who
want to
step in
to steward
in our participatory context
are going to be leverage points for so
many more people who come through
so there's like multiple levels of
affordances for those who see them
especially at the end of this section
and
it's been quite a few months
any
last comments
okay i'm gonna stop the recording in
three seconds unless somebody wants to
say something
okay